Hello.
Welcome to the time I.S. and its very first lesson of the section.
We are going to see how to create precise delays using timers.
So I'm going to create a new project and this project is going to enable a hardware timer to provide
us with delay, basically.
So I'm going to select my board.
If you have that this call you select the disk will help the new clothes.
Also, like this double click.
And then I'll do the usual stuff.
So first, start off by cleaning everything here.
Clipping out.
And then this time, Hobaugh, you post the video and initialize the RCC to what we often initialize
it to, as well as the, uh, select a zero wire for the debugging.
Okay.
Once you out, you've done that, you can impose.
And then we do.
Right.
The usual stuff.
Here.
RACC, HSC, ojars.
Bypass.
And then lo LSC.
Or see you ceramic crystal.
And then.
Okay.
Once that is done.
We said we're going to initialize a time.
So we come to timers.
We've got a number of times we're going to use timer to.
So click time or two over here.
So once you click, if it doesn't open, you've got to expand it from here.
We need to select the clock source of the time.
That's very important.
So when I use the internal clock, so I'll click over here to select this.
And before we forget, we said we want to do a delay, so be nice to use the delay to talk to our lady.
So we are going to enable all ality for the output.
So P a five.
So LCD.
Right.
Click over here.
Keep your output.
And like always, we'd rename it or call it ality.
Like this.
Right.
So we've got to figure out what time I hear the unit, et cetera.
But before we do that, let's take a look at the, um, the clock frequency of all time.
Of course, we know that to perform this type of configuration.
I'm going to come to clock configuration over here.
And we said we are using our what time are two.
So, all right.
Here we have the.
Does the default clock, 84 megahertz.
And then when we come here, we get a clock for the various peripherals.
It says MPB to time our clocks is at eighty four megahertz and then EPB one per four o'clock.
And then there's EPB one timer clocks.
And then there is EPB to appear before a clock.
Right.
So the question becomes, is how a timer EPB to Taimur or APB one Tyber that we need to find out?
So to find that out, we can go and take a look at the data sheet of the reference of the microcontroller,
not the reference manual.
This will help us.
There are so many documents out there.
We can take a look at the, um, the data sheet and then that will tell us what.
OK.
I know the answer to this.
I can just move on and, you know, and then see, OK.
This is what time I.
It's connected to this puzzle.
But I think I should show you.
So we have to divert a bit.
Let's go back to our best friend, Google and get the data sheet.
All right.
This the most practical course you would you ever take.
So we need SDM 32 F for one one this time, not reference my door data sheet.
It's a different document.
Okay, let's see who says PDAF.
Estimate three to four.
OK.
Oh, come here.
It doesn't say PDAF, but it might lead us to the PDAF.
I'll put PDAF in the search PDAF over here.
This is reference my No.
We need a data sheet.
Okay, let's come to the S-T Web site.
But for one, one, OK, no problem.
Thank you very much.
Let's go to Resources.
Go for a few.
OK.
So if we were using call you vision, call you vision has a tap for all the documents you would ever
require for a particular microcontroller.
But that's not a case we use in Cuba, Max, in Cuba already.
So we've got to find this.
Okay.
So we can try another link.
No, this is not official stuff, I'm going to post the video, find the appropriate link, and then
we open it together.
Could you believe the thing was at the top here all along?
There's the link.
We're looking for a STEM 32 resource data sheet.
Okay.
Right.
Click open over here.
Okay.
So what we need here is a block diagram that tells us about the bus connection of the microcontroller,
how the various the various peripherals are connected to the bus.
Okay.
Yeah, we go.
This is what we're looking for.
Page number 15.
And, um, zoom in.
So this diagram here is very important.
This tells us which bus connects to which peripheral.
So in arm, there are basically two buses, four connecting the C.P.U to the other peripherals.
And they are two because they have different current characteristics.
One is faster than the other.
We have the HP bus, which is known as the Advanced High Peripheral Bus.
And we have the APB bus, which is I think known as advance prep for a bus.
The APB is a legacy version.
It's older.
The HP is the newer.
And the HP allows us to access the various parts or peripherals at a higher frequency.
So the APB has a lower frequency compared to the HP.
And you can find this out actually as it is written here.
Over here.
Let's see.
It says APB, too.
Who are we dealing with?
Let's see.
Which microcontrollers this esteemed.
Three to four.
One one.
Okay.
So this is HP, one hundred megahertz.
HP 200 megahertz.
APB 150 mega hits, it just so happens that over here we have an APB also with a 100 megahertz, but
often.
A HB allows for foster access so you can have the same pair for which you can have a single pair for
all.
And you can either access that single pair for it or by HP or APB.
So when you act, when you want to access it faster with less clock cycles, should opt for the AHP.
But if regular speed, regular frequency is what you want.
You stick to the APB.
So that's the difference between the two.
So we said we want to know where our time on the time.
Are we dealing with where it is connected?
So to know where a particular pair fros connected.
Which plus it is connected.
You just need to follow the arrows like it is said an investigation.
Follow the money.
This over here.
We follow the arrows.
So, for instance, we've got G.P.A. reports.
When you see there's an arc connecting keuper your ports e to this other bus here and where you take
a look at the name of the bus.
It is HP one.
So if we want to know where G.P.A. ports is connected, it is connected to HP one.
And in fact, all the GPL use are connected to HP one bus.
OK.
So let's run the same experiment for our time.
We said we work with time or two.
When we take a look at time or two over here, we see the arrow connecting to time or two when we see
the other side of the arm.
What does it connect to?
It connects to APB one.
So APB one maximum frequency is 50 megahertz.
So as you can see, time two is APB.
One frequency is connected to APB, one bus.
And we find this in the data sheet.
No, the reference nor remember the reference manual or what, 800 pages.
This one is just a little over.
Or maybe, you know, a hundred and a half pages.
One hundred and forty nine pages in total.
So let's save this as well so that the next time we require it, we wouldn't go looking for it.
Okay.
It's downloaded.
I'm going to minimize this.
So timer two is connected to APB one bus.
Okay, so when we come over here, given our current configuration, let's see, it says APB one time
a clock.
So our APB one time a clock currently is 84 megahertz.
Eight people, one time a clock is what we use in.
You can put.
Yeah.
Let's see this again.
We cannot debug all of these together.
OK.
So the reason I'm back here is because it says fifty megahertz, Max.
But Cuba, Max here is telling us it's set it's to its default frequency at 84 megahertz.
You see it before.
So it turns out they're 50 megahertz.
Doesn't apply to the time.
As you can see, the APB, one bus has other peripherals connected to it as well.
We have the eye to see three eye to see two Aspey, three Espey to another of another pair for us.
We have the, um, the ROTC, the real time clock as well.
So there is this part over here, the card.
Yet it says the time is connected to APB to uncloaked from time X clock up to 100 megahertz whilst the
time is connected to APB one clock from time X clock up to one hundred megahertz.
So this implies that our time is clocked up to one hundred megahertz.
That is why we could have time to two on APB bus, which says 50 megahertz max here.
But in Cuba makes the default is set us eighty four, which is within the range.
If we take this sentence here into account.
OK.
So.
Right.
That being said, um, where are we.
Back to Cuba, Max.
And I hope you find this useful rather than me just telling you it's APB, one bus and then we perform
the divisions, so.
OK.
This is APB, one bus, and it's currently clocked at 84 megahertz.
So our goal is to bring our timer into the millisecond unit.
It's time.
Currently it's eighty four megahertz.
Mega implies a million.
Eighty four megahertz implies 84 million.
This means 84 million.
Cycos, uh, executed in a single second.
That is warheads applies or Kerans in a second.
That implies up implies a second.
So meaning 84 megahertz means 84 million.
Cycos in a second.
So we know in one second gives us eighty four million.
Therefore, we can deduce that.
One millisecond would require eighty four thousand.
Course, we know a thousand milliseconds gives us a second.
Eighty four million Cycos in one second.
How many psychos in one millisecond, 84000 psychos.
Right.
I'm gonna come over here and then our time a priest killer, I'm gonna put it to 4000 here.
It's you four with three zeros.
One, two, three.
So what happens is this pre-schooler value is this would divide the time of frequency by this pre-schooler
value.
So our time frequency is currently at 84 million.
And then we had divide in it by eighty four thousand.
When we'd performed that division, we would have 1000.
Then we've brought it to the millisecond range.
That is what we're doing here.
Leave a comment in the Q&A section.
If you do not understand this.
So now our timer is in millisecond range.
What we have to set is the time as the counter period, the counter period.
This is what would determine the time out.
When should the time out?
OK.
So we have milliseconds.
Let's see.
We want if we want 10 milliseconds every 10 milliseconds, we'll put 10 over here because.
Oh, I forgot this one here.
Oh.
Forty eight thousand.
One, two, three.
We need to hit enter.
OK, so now our timer is in millisecond range, one millisecond range.
And what I mean by one, we derive that by the.
The.
Sorry.
This.
Should it be.
Forty eight thousand.
I'm all over the place.
Eighty four thousand just to show you.
We went through this.
Eighty four million divided by the eighty four thousand gives us 1000 APB.
One is at it for me.
Go ahead.
Which means 84 million to divide that by.
Eighty four thousand you get 1000.
And this has brought us from second to milliseconds.
Cause a thousand milliseconds gives us a second.
Right.
So then our timer is in milliseconds.
When I come here.
Oh, I see.
The pre-schooler value, it has to be, he has to be.
He has to be sixteen, um, a sixteen bit value.
So that is why when we put eighty four thousand there, we're not quite getting it.
OK, let's see.
I'm gonna see whether indeed our clock is what it is.
Right.
Um, our clock looks fine.
Yeah.
So, okay, this accept a 16 bit value for it.
Um, it's input, the highest number you can enter the sixteen bit.
So we cannot enter it in four thousand.
See, the largest sixteen bit value is sixty five thousand five hundred and thirty six.
That is what that is.
Why when we enter eighty four thousand it doesn't accept.
So okay we can all use that as a preschooler.
So okay we experimented together.
So rather than bring our timer down to millisecond range, we can bring it into, um, ten milliseconds
range.
Tens.
Tens of milliseconds.
So each unit, rather than being a millisecond, will be 10 milliseconds.
And, um, let's see how you would get this.
So remember, we set our clock, which we have over here is the same.
Oh.
If the datasheet information.
No, we we collected is accurate.
The information we interpret it if it's accurate.
And given what we see over here.
Oh.
EPB one time a clock.
It could be one time a clocks is.
Eighty four megahertz.
If this is indeed the case this means eighty four million.
And this further means eighty four million psychos are executed in one second.
That is what Hertz implies.
Hertz implies a second.
So.
Eighty four million cycles executed in one second.
So the question becomes one or the number of cycles executed.
And one second, is it four million?
How many cycles will be executed?
And let's see, one millisecond.
Okay.
We know a thousand milliseconds make one second.
Therefore, that value is eighty four thousand.
So the question is further asked.
Eighty four thousand for one millisecond.
Then how many cycles do we think will be executed in ten milliseconds.
In 10 milliseconds.
Actually, um, we can avoid all of this complicated explanation just by bringing our war time down
for the range.
OK.
So I'm gonna change the time frequency here from it.
Eighty four gigahertz so that I do not have to start using ten milliseconds as units.
And that's very important.
Is good that you see this entire process.
I could have just, you know, stop this video and then figure it out.
What a simple explanation.
And they shot a fresh video that moves straight forward.
But I want you to appreciate some of the experimentation that goes on.
Well, you are dealing with a board and there is no example.
And you've got to sort of write it by yourself.
So what I'm gonna do here, over here.
You're the one timer.
The system has set it to eighty four megahertz.
I'm gonna put it to forty eight megahertz.
Right.
So I just had this.
Forty eight megahertz.
A lot of things have changed as well.
Our system clock has changed from its eighty four megahertz to ninety six megahertz.
Right.
And then other peripherals of change.
But time is the only one we interested in.
So now our timer is at forty eight megahertz, meaning forty eight million cycles in a second.
In a single second, forty eight minute cycles.
Therefore, in a millisecond.
Then we'll have forty eight thousand cycles so we can simply go and then divide a while.
Thirty eight to make ahead by forty eight thousand.
To bring our time into the millisecond range.
So I'll come over here.
Okay.
We have forty eight thousand here.
This is our killer.
The killer is used to divide the time of frequency.
So with this preschooler we would have forty eight million divided by forty eight thousand.
And when we get will be 1000.
Right.
So now our time eyes in the millisecond range.
So the day count period is.
When we want to the time, our tool kit, if we want a timeout, too.
Okay.
Every 10 milliseconds I can pass 10 over here.
If I wanted to.
Okay.
Over here, every hundred millisecond I can pass one hundred if I want every thousand millisecond.
Which means every second.
Then I can pass 1000 here.
Right.
And I hope you appreciate the um.
The process, the brainstorming that you know we've done together.
Or do you know.
Yeah, sure.
You've been brainstorming along remotely.
I should say.
So this is what we going to keep.
We could have, you know, kept our 84 million.
And then used other units that would fit into our sixteen bit value.
But we can just bring the clock down.
And then we can use this if you don't understand how to use the pre-schooler in the current period.
Um, you can leave in the Q&A section.
Right.
So another thing we have to do is said the trigger events election.
And over here, we're going to keep select updates, events so that you would keep updated.
So what are three things we did?
Is the pre-schooler the.
The auto reload over here.
It's just 10.
It should be 1000.
The auto reload, which is 1000.
And then the update event.
Right.
Over here, we can set the auto reload preload also to enable.
Yeah.
Let's move on.
Once this is done, we come to NVC and then we enable a timer to global interrupt like this.
So now we're ready to generate our code.
We come to project manager or select my two chain is the.
It's the cube idea.
And then we can give the project a name.
Call this time delay.
Right.
And then a click here to generate a code.
Once this is done, click open project over here.
So this project or just clean up a bit.
So, OK, that's what we have.
So that's our main function.
This time we initialised upl you and then we initialise time are to us.
Well, the definition of this function is down here, Terma.
And this is basically the selections we made.
This is our pre-schooler value.
If we want to change it, we can change from here.
This is the period we set as well.
If we want to change the.
That also can be changed from here.
Right.
Okay.
So let's see.
What we have to do is first start our time.
I interrupt.
Let's go to our what time I drive up and see the functions available.
I'll click over here on Drivers Hall.
And then the source over here.
I'll click how time I dot h o t i m this one here.
I m dot c..
Over here I should say that I will click this open in a large file.
Scalability mode has been turned on for.
Okay.
I'll say yes.
Applying clues.
The file is very large.
It says so.
Click over here to see the outline.
Over here, it says the outline is disabled due to scalability, MODOK, click options.
Disable ed, pass in.
This is what disable the hotline.
OK.
So let's not spend time here.
We're looking for a function to help us start the, um, the the timer.
First, we've got to start the timer interrupt and then we proceed from there so we can do it manually
by finding it.
Oh, we can go to the, um, the reference manual we downloaded.
Okay, so let's look for it next time.
I'm not going to open it.
Scalability.
OK.
So this is it starts the time-based generation in interrupt mode.
So the whole time bathes in it.
So this is the function we pass the time we pass the address of the time, a handler argument and then
it returns the time a status typedef.
So I'm gonna copy this controversy over here to copy and then I'll come to Main and then over here after
we've initialize the time, are we going to the time line defined by here, time out to a.T.M to sort
of copy this and then pass it over here.
Right.
So we have this next, because our timeline is set as an interrupt every second as we configured, we
said the time should OK.
Every second.
So every second a block of code in D callback function is going to be executed.
What we need to do next is find the header or the structure of this callback function just like we did.
For what other interrupt example for GPL?
Your input interrupt.
We had a callback function and then we put out what do something like block of code inside a callback
such that whenever the interrupt occurs, our piece of code is executed.
We've got to do the same thing here whenever the interrupt occurs.
The piece of code that we want to execute would would execute.
But this time to interrupt that or caires is triggered by the time event.
Whereas in the GPL, for example, the interrupt was triggered by that, a rising edge or the fallen
edge of the switch.
Meaning when we press this switch, something changes from high to low or low to high.
And by that detection, we we trigger the interrupt.
But this time, it's going to be triggered by time every second.
OK, so we go back to our time a module.
The function is call a period, a lapse of time, a period elapsed the C.
It's over here.
Line four thousand eight hundred two such very quickly.
You can just to control F and then you search for a keyword just like we do, OK?
So it?
S also has the weak keyword here.
And when we explain what we have.
By that we keyword to what we have to do is copy this callback function and then reimplemented.
Now what we.
OK.
So if he has a spirit loves call back in non blocking mode.
Right.
So I'm going to copy this controversy to copy.
Come to Main and then paste this over here.
I'll just paste that.
You can paste it anywhere.
And then in here we can talk about ality.
If you have an algorithm that you want to compute every second, you can put it over here.
If you have other things you want to do every second.
Basically do something.
Whenever you have a callback, you can pull whatever you want to do that.
Over here, we happen to be using LCD for our sort of computation.
We're using the LCD to be like a war complex algorithm that is supposed to be executed when interrupt.
OK.
So in here we can torgau the LCD by seeing how on a score GPL you should be Cupps all on a score GPA.
You on the score torgau pin.
And then we need to find the um deport.
The early DGP, a port.
I don't want to make his Pelin mistake.
So the first argument is the port.
And then the second argument is the pin, which is simply the lady pin.
Right.
So this all we have to do
so quickly to boot.
Well, here.
And then we've got some errors.
Oh, I still have the weak keyword here.
Okay.
Click here to build.
You still have errors.
See?
OK.
Over here.
We had to pass the address, not just this small, I had to bring The Ambersons sign all time base.
If you take a look at the function, the function takes the address.
So I went to see if this would fix all our problems.
OK.
We've got problems fixed.
Why not run it by clicking here?
OK.
Says Arrow Initialise in Besty Link.
Okay, we'll take a look at that.
Of reconnected my boat.
I'm going to click here to go back to the debugger.
You know, click here to run.
And as you can see, my LCD is toppling at a one second toco rate, just like we set our timer configuration.
So that's all there is for this lesson, if you have any questions at all.
Just let me know and I'll see you later.
Have a nice day.